Walker Family papers, Inclusive:1836-1916, undated, Bulk: 1861-1885, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Walker Family papers
Inclusive:1836-1916, undated, Bulk: 1861-1885, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
248
Walker, William Collett
8 folders.
The Walker Family papers consist of correspondence, legal, financial, and photographic materials from various family members, especially James Frances Walker Jr. and William Collett Walker.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
James Frances Walker Jr. (1793-1873) resident of Kentucky, married Abler Collett Walker (died 1831) in 1816. They had four children while in Kentucky, with a fifth born in Texas. The Walker family arrived in Texas in 1824 as part of Stephen F. Austin's Old Three Hundred colony, and James served in the Texian army in the Texas Revolution. Originally settling in Washington County, the family moved to Waco in the early 1850s.
The only male child of James and Abler Walker, William Collett Walker (1818-1896), married Rebecca Briscoe Cobbs Walker (1836-1916), daughter of the local county judge, in 1854. William and Rebecca had five children: Ella A. Walker Patterson (1855-1943), Charlotte Virginia Walker (1860-1886), William Collett Walker (1864-1941), Hallie Rebecca Walker Wheeler (1872-1918), and Thomas Cobbs Walker (1877-1902). Several of the children attended Waco Classical School, Academy of the Sacred Heart, and Baylor University. All of the children stayed in the McLennan County area, and most family members who passed away in Waco area are buried in the Cobbs-Walker Cemetery in Waco, Texas.
Scope and Content
The Walker Family papers consist of a variety of materials from different family members, together with the financial records of William Collett Walker. The Walker family seems to have been quite wealthy, and this is reflected in the collection with documents related to land transactions, bills and receipts, and photographs of family members. There is a group photograph of a class from the Academy of the Sacred Heart, and a portrait of a family member who attended Baylor University. Included in the financial papers are a receipt for attending Waco Classical School, and several receipts for paying taxes to the local Confederate government during the Civil War. Notable in this collection are multiple bills of sale for enslaved people.
Arrangement
The Walker Family papers were arranged in folders with titles at the time of current processing. No date ranges were present. Some materials are in protective sleeves.
Currently, the Walker Family papers are arranged in four series: I. Correspondence, II. Legal, III. Financial, and IV. Photographs.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 248. Acquired 1978-10-23
Related Resources
Related references
Find A Grave, Inc. "William Collett Walker." Memorial #18997401. Databases. Accessed 2020 June 30.
Hafertepe, Kenneth. Historic Homes of Waco, Texas. College Station: Texas A&M Press, 2019.
Texas Historical Commission. "Cobbs-Walker Cemetery," McLennan County, Historical Marker #5309000926. Texas Historical Commission Database. Accessed 2020 June 30.
Index Terms
Places
Texas -- Photographs.
Subjects
Bills of sale.; Slavery -- Texas.
Genres
Correspondence.; Financial records.; Legal documents.; Photographs.
- Correspondence, 1867-1916; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Unknown.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains letters written by various members of the Walker family. The series is in average condition.
  - Letters, 1867-1916 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Legal, 1890; 2
  This series contains a land title for multiple blocks in the University Heights area of Waco, Texas. The series is in poor condition.
  - Abstract of title, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Financial, 1836-1881; 3
  This series contains bills and receipts and a bill of sale for enslaved people. This series is in average condition.
  - Bills and Receipts, 1836-1881 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bills of sale for enslaved people, 1847, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Photographs, 1885, undated; 4
  This series contains portrait photographs and a few group photographs of the Walker family in and around Waco, Texas. Of particular note is a photograph of the Academy of the Sacred Heart, a Catholic school in Waco, Texas. This series is in good condition.
  - Academy of the Sacred Heart, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Portraits from Waco area (1 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Portraits from Waco area (2 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)